Now that we've seen how redirections work.
We can use this system
to keep on handling our files.
Let's have a look at a very simple command
called "sort". It'll allow you to sort what you're giving it as arguments.
So in this case,
what you write on the standard input.
So here we can see it's sorted all users
alphabetically.
Be careful, this is a sorting that we call
"lexicographic", which means
it's based on ASCII's characters sorting, so uppercases are before lowercases
To... not have this behavior, you've got options to sort numbers...
There are also options to sort in reverse. Do a "man sort",
and check out all of its options.
Once you've sorted your output, you'll be able to retrieve just the
first names, for example.
In order to do that, you'll need the "cut" command, which will allow you to
cut each line depending on a delimiter.
So for example, if I "cut" with the option "-d" on a delimiter, I'll be able to
retrieve the fields I've chosen, and if I only want the first fields,
I'll just have to add "-f" with "1".
As we've seen earlier on,
If I add "cat -e" to display non-printable characters
I can see that there's a space after "maxime" here.
Something I wouldn't have noticed without "cat -e".
The "cut" command is very powerful. It'll allow you to do many things.
For example, retrieve multiple fields. You may also do a field sort.
That should be quite practical to retrieve only infos that are important to you ...
in files like this, that'll be separated by the same delimiter (dot, comma, etc...)
Once you've managed to get this result,
let's say we keep those first names, we'll be able to modify them.
For example, if I want to change "thomas" by "Thomas"
I can use the "sed" command, which is a very, very powerful command
which allows you to make modifications on data flow.
For example you can ask it to turn "thomas" into "Thomas".
As we can see here, "Thomas" starts with a capital letter.
So what does it do? The first character, the "s"
means we're going to "substitute".
meaning we're going to replace our 2nd parameter by our 3rd parameter.
It's really simple.
This is basic "sed" functionalities.
However, we can do much more. I'll let you check it out for yourselves.
Go have a look at examples on the internet.
You can also do "one out of two" modifications. We call those "regex".
"regex" are on "patterns", which also are very powerful if you know how to use them.
The last file-modification command that we'll see,
is called "tr"
For example, here we can see the accent in "mélanie".
I want to replace it by a normal "e"... "tr" is very simple: it takes 2 arguments,
a character and the one we're replacing it with.
For example, if we use an "x" to replace the lowercase one in "xavier"...
It works.
All those commands are pretty basic. Once again, check out their "man".
Check out the internet and test them out for yourselves to learn how they work.