Welcome to the bonus part of the day.
This part isn't mandatory for today's exercises.
But it'll be useful for your career as a developer.
And for the rest of the bootcamp too.
So earlier we talked about standard output
Actually, it isn't 100% accurate...
There are two types of outputs : standard output, and standard error.
So using our favorite example : "cat file.txt"
Everything went fine, the file's content is displayed on the standard output.
However, if try doing "cat" on a file that doesn't exist,
it'll display a message on the error output.
Let's say I do a "cat file.txt | rev"
The file's being displayed in reverse.
Which means the file's content has been displayed on the standard output.
The pipe's interpreted the standard output as the "rev"'s standard input
and the "rev" has done its job.
However, if I do this on a file that doesn't exist...
cat will display the error on the standard error channel,
"rev" won't read from this error channel, as it only reads from the standard output,
which is now its standard input, so the message won't be displayed.
It can be interesting. Or not.
You may also reverse the error message if you want.
How? By adding more redirections,
If we want to redirect the standard error channel's message, and handle it
as if it was a standard output, we'll do this...
So 2 represents the standard error's output.
the 1 represents the standard output. We tell it that everything there is on
the standard error channel has to be treated as if it was a standard output.
So, if we add " | rev ", we can see the message is in reverse.
Because it's been treated like a standard output.
Identically, we can redirect everything that's in the standard error channel (2)
into a file.
For example, if I do this ... I'm asking 2 to be redirected into "error"
and keep everything that's in "error".
we can see our earlier error message
And once again, if we do this 2-3 times in a row,
it's only displayed once, because it's been overwritten and there's a double redirection,
which will allow you to place your error messages at the end of the file.
All of this can be quite practical if you have a list of files containing
error messages, but you want to keep only the part that worked
or only the part that didn't work, etc...
Thanks to those redirections, you'll be able to gather all erroneous files
into one error file.
Something else, that may be useful... a very special file ...
that isn't really a file, but oh well... It's called "/dev/null"
What is it? Basically, everything that's written
towards "/dev/null" will simply be erased. Forgotten.
So here, nothing's gonna happen. The "/dev/null" file doesn't really exist.
So nothing's been added to it. Whatever.
So what can we use it for? We can use it to delete a part,
and keep only error messages, for example.
If we want to display all error messages,
it's a real mess. You need to go back up, check, and stuff...
If we tell it "everything worked, redirect this towards /dev/null" ...
and there you go! Displaying only error messages.
So once again, this may be very practical for debugging
or check whether your scripts work as they should.
That's something very important to know for the future.