Hello everyone, and welcome to this lesson : C in 42 minutes (almost)
Before anything, small clarification : this lesson is not meant
to teach you how to program in C.
It's not an exhaustive description of the language.
Its sole purpose is to bring forward
elements you'll need to complete this piscine.
It's a subset of C, which will allow you
to accomplish everything that's asked of you during this piscine.
Before even starting to write code,
the 1st thing you need to understand is...
What's a computer? What's in it?
And how does it work?
So, a machine is made of 3 elements.
The first is the CPU.
It's the one that processes all calculations, all comparisons, ...
All of these actions are made by the CPU.
The second element is the RAM.
The RAM is a tool, an object that'll hold
everything that's been memorised by the computer.
So this second element is very important.
And last, the 3rd element is made of computer peripherals/devices.
That's what will allow you to connect your computer to the rest of the world.
So we have those 3 elements.
These 3 elements are interlinked by a system, called BUS
which will allow information to be transferred.
There's also a clock system,  which allows all of this to operate together.
So, of course a computer is much more
complex than what I've described.
But that's, I would say, the image.
or at least the representation we'll need
during the rest of this piscine,
and also, for a while, during 1st year at the school.
So let's keep this basic description for now.
I'll say it again:
a processor (CPU), so a treatment unit, a memorisation system,
which we call RAM, and a system of interface with the rest of the world
in other words, devices.
And programming, what does it mean?
Programming, in the end, compared to what we've seen before,
meaning the paradigm of the computer's description,
consists in giving instructions to the processor,
meaning a list of elementary actions
which will handle data.
So we'll be able to do extremely simple actions.
Like, for example, comparing two data,
a simple operation such as an addition, a subtraction or a division.
We'll be able to relay an information in a new address,
so, we'll be able to copy the data of an address into another.
We'll be able to do basic arithmetics,
basic comparisons, and we'll be able to
send these data to a device, for example, display them onscreen,
or simply forward them.
What you need to understand, is that we're trying to do things
that are extremely elementary, but that will be done extremely fast
and in a very large quantity.
These elementary instructions will allow us to simulate extremely
complicated behaviors, maybe even
simulate intelligence.
However, today, our programming sytem
won't be able to just do extremely elementary things.
So what about C in all that?
In the end, the computer will process a language, which is called
computer-language, which is a very elementary language,
directly made of codes that are particularly unpleasant
for human beings.
The C language is a layer above of this.
It's a relatively simple language, that's close to
the computer's language.
Here, we'll have a sequential language which will, overall,
have a translation in rather elementary operations.
So nothing too complicated.
However, it'll be readable and pretty simple to use
by a human being.
which will make this process efficient.
So, we have a system that will be complicated,
meaning we'll transform the C language into something we write
in computer language.
Then, this computer language will be executed by the processor,
and it'll be readable by human beings,
and it'll compile (so it's particularly efficient) all by letting a set of
functionalities, that are relatively evolved, allowing us to
function correctly.
Another important layer to integrate,
is the operating system.
The operating system is the software
that'll make the computer work.
It'll be launched at the start-up, and will allow us
to have an interface between the user and the machine.
The OS,
we'll see more complex definitions and descriptions later on,
because it's a very complex object that's been elaborated with a lot
of work for a very long time,
The OS is the result of a strong evolution.
This object will manage the entire functioning of the computer
and your program will 'interface" itself with the OS.
To be clear, when, for example, you'll want to display a character,
your program, written in C, will tells the OS
via what we call system-calls,
"I want this character to be displayed"
And it's the OS that'll do the job.
Which means, in your program, you don't need to code
the entire system, that'll lead
to displaying a character.
So, C will allow your to write simple instructions,
which will allow you to "interface" with the OS, which will also
"interface" itself with the hardware
to display or to cary out the actions you need.
As we've seen previously, the computer holds memory,
so it holds data, and will be able
to run processes on these data, so follow instructions.
A C program, is the representation of not only data we'll process,
which means we'll have information about these data,
but also instructions.
In the RAM, we'll depict the data by groups of 8,
which we call bytes.
It's a group of 8 bits, so 8, 1 and 0, we'll call that a byte.
It allows us to represent numbers from 0 to 255,
depending on their representation.
and each of these bytes, will be given an address,
which will allow us to recognise it, and find it.
C will allow us to work on these bytes,
and so work on the address system.
C uses types to represent data,
and so we'll have several types.
The first type, is what we call CHAR,
which is 8-bit, so a byte.
So it can represent numbers from -128 to +127,
and a basic arithmetics is affected to it,
which will allow it to handles all usual processes:
divisions, subtractions, etc...
The second type is the UNSIGNED CHAR,
which is also 8 bits, but that'll have another representation,
which will go from 0 to 255.
Then, you have what we call a SHORT, which is 2 bytes,
out of 16-bits, which will allow us to represent
from - 32 000 up to +32 000.
You also have the UNSIGNED SHORT, skipping details...
You have the INT, which is on 4 bytes,
and it generally is the data structure
we use the most, because it
allows us to do most processes.
You also have the UNSIGNED INT,
the LONG, and the LONG LONG,
which allow us to represent data
up to 64 bits.
You have the UNSIGNED LONG...
And you have the last type, which is called the "star", "asterisk"
or "pointer", which allows to hold
not just a data, but the address of a data.
We can consider that a data's address is also a data itself,
but there's a special arithmetic that we'll see later on.
Now that we know how to represent data,
let's start talking about a program's structure.
A program's structure, is a set of functions.
What we call a function,
is an entity said to be closed because
data in this entity
are supposed to be closed
to the rest of the world, which get this information,
which we call parameters, and which
will return a result, and between the two
we have a process, and we'll see how it works.
A function is always made of
two things: instructions, and local variables.
Here, you see the first syntax element :
the declaration of a function.
A function can be declared rather simply.
We define its type, meaning the type of what the function returns,
because a function takes values as entries
which we call parameters, and returns a result.
So the type you see first on this prototype,
is the return value's type.
Then we have the function's name,
and then the list of parameters, which are
every time, the type of the 1st parameter,
the name of the 1st parameter,
the type of the 2nd parameter,
the name of the 2nd parameter,
etc, etc...
There can be as many parameters as we want,
there can also be none at all.
If there's no parameter, we simply write
opening parenthesis, closing parenthesis.
That is what defines what the function returns,
and what it takes for parameters, and right after,
there's what we call a block.
A block contains the function itself.
A function is always split into two parts.
The second part, the block, is between curly brackets.
So there's an opening curly bracket, the declaration of local variables,
followed by instructions,
- There could be only one instruction, there could be no local variable,
there could be no instruction -
and we always end with a closing curly bracket.
Here's a quick example
of a small function. Here we'll declare
a function called sum(), which returns an int,
and which takes 2 parameters:
a parameter "value1", which is of type int,
and a 2nd parameter "value2", which is also an int.
This function starts it block, so opening curly bracket.
"int total" declares a new int called "total",
and is a local variable to the function.
The functions are closed,
which means outside of the function, this variable doesn't exist.
Therefore, it's local.
Then we've got the instructions
In this example, there aren't any, but that's where they'd be.
And finally, the closing curly bracket: end of the block, end of the function.
In C, we can declare what we call combined types.
They're data structures which are made of
elementary types, which we saw earlier on.
There are a few, but during this piscine,
we'll only use 2.
The first is the array.
An array is a succession of objects
of the same type (in the memory).
It's easily declared: type, name,
opening square bracket, number of elements in the array,
closing square bracket.
You've got an example on the right :
"int tab[42]", which is the declaration of an array,
which can contain 42 ints.
The array's index goes from 0 to 41.
We always start at 0.
So, with this array,
you've reserved 42 ints in the memory.
To access them, we write the name, opening square bracket,
the number of the int we want, closing square bracket.
For example, if we write "int tab[12]", we'll get the 13th int.
The second combined type is a bit more complex,
and we'll use it later on, is called data structure.
The structure will allow us to define the representation of an object in memory,
which will be made of basic elements, that could very well be
structures too.
You have to know we can interlink structures, arrays, etc...
Let's check out how to declare a structure.
we write "struct", the name of our structure, opening curly bracket,
we declare this structure's components (type, name, etc...)
closing curly bracket and semi-colon.
Here, we've just declared a structure.
There's an example on the right,
where we declare a structure "s_fortytwo".
It's made of an int called "a",
and an array of 21 characters,
called "b".
We define it in a simple manner, indicated below.
We declare the structure,
and when we write "struct", name of the structure,
name of the variable, semi-colon, it reserves the necessary memory area,
and when we use this name, the program will know
we're talking about a structure.
The compiler in C is usually pretty permissive.
In terms of syntax, you can write things
in many different ways.
But to make things more readable,
and have some sort of consistency,
we've defined a standard (Norm).
This standard will be presented later on.
You'll have a specific lesson on this topic.
It's important for you to understand that using this standard
has a lot of advantages.
The 1st advantage is that it allows you to easily read
each others code.
The 2nd is that it helps learn how to program
in a structured way.
You'll see that even if you've already programmed before,
the school's standard will still be an adjustment.
It's biggest advantage is that it gives us a
"look and feel" and helps for the reading.
When we'll read someone else's code,
being used to a standard will allow us to read faster.
We please respect it.
We have a program that checks whether the standard's been respected.
We've seen that a program was a set of functions,
and that there can be many functions.
So where to start from?
It has been defined,
that in C syntax, originally,
the function that will be executed first, the one that'll trigger
the program's execution, is the function main().
So if you create a program,
somewhere in your code, there'll be a function main().
It's a function that takes a certain number of parameters,
you'll see later how they work and how to use them.
main() returns an int, but you'll see how this also works.
This way, you'll systematically have this declaration :
"int main", the parameters between parenthesis, if there are any,
and the function's block.
Now that we've seen the general structure of a program,
and we've seen how to represent data,
all that remains is how instructions work.
Of course, now that we know how to declare data,
we need to learn how to act on these data.
It's quite simple.
There are 3 types of instructions.
There's what we call "blocks", which, as we've seen,
are always made of an opening curly bracket,
a collection of local variable declarations (local to the block),
instructions which will be executed by that block,
and a closing curly bracket.
There's also what we call "expressions",
which will be followed by a semi-colon,
and make a numerical calculation, or evaluation, happen.
We'll go into this later on.
And then, we have what we call "control structures",
which allows to control the proceedings
of a series of instructions, inside a block.
Let's start with expressions.
So, expressions, as we've said,
are a set of evaluations, which will give results.
The simplest of evaluations, is a numerical value.
For example, if you wrote a number, here 0 and 42,
you can write it in hex (0XA), in octal (010),
and it'll evaluate itself to its own value.
meaning that the compiler will make sure it's worth its result.
The 2nd type of expression: Variables,
Once we've got a variable, when we use it,
it'll go evaluate directly to the variable's value.
If, for instance, you have a value in an int "a",
like in the example,
when you write "a", it'll be worth the value that's in "a".
Same thing for an array : If you wrote b[18],
it'll look for the 19th element,
held in "b".
In the case of a structure,
if you have a structure element called "sft_var.a",
it'll look for the element "a" in the structure "sft_var".
So a variable is evaluated directly by the value it contains.
The 3rd type of expression is what we call function calls.
We write the name of the function,
the parameters we'll pass to this function,
the compiler will call the function,
and it'll be evaluated to the function's return value.
We've seen that a function takes parameters for entry,
does the process we ask it to do, and returns a value.
So this value will be set instead of the function.
In the following calculation, we'll have a function.
We can combine all these elements thanks to computations.
This way, the compiler will process the arithmetics,
and, as you can see below, we can write
very complicated things.
If you write "1 + 3" it'll take the 1, and add 3 to it,
"-", it handles parenthesis and priorities, operations,
there's a b[0] which will get the first element of the array "b",
when it'll write "a x 42", it'll go get the value of "a",
it'll divide by the sum of 2 elements,
returned by the function sum().
The compiler will manage to evaluate, calculate,
the result of these arithmetic expressions
and will do it in the right order.
The last type of expressions : Assignations.
An assignation, is, for instance, when we write "a = 42".
The compiler will set the value "42" to the variable "a",
and will return, as a result, 42.
We'll systematically have an assignation and an evaluation.
For example, if you write "b[2 + a]",
we'll go get the value contained in "a",
and add 2 to it.
This value serves as an index,
to go read in the array "b".
We'll calculate the result of the function that's on the right,
we'll assign it in the array,
and we'll return, as a result, the function's result.
It's an assignation, and it'll modify the data in the variable.
There are other expressions.
We have what we call comparisons.
A comparison in C, is an operator which will be evaluated,
just like any other expression, to a value.
We call TRUE, the return value 1,
and FALSE, the return value 0.
So when you write, for instance, "a == b",
it'll check if the content of variable "a"
is equal to the content of variable "b".
If both contents are equal, it'll return 1, else it'll return 0.
All comparators work the same way.
Another example, if you write "a < b",
it'll check the values of "a" and "b",
if "a" is indeed inferior to "b", it'll return 1, else it'll return 0.
As operators, you have "==", which compares equality,
"!=" means "different than", "", "=", "||" (logical OR),
"&&" (logical AND) and "!!" which is a negation.
If we write "!a", if "a" is worth 0, then it return 1,
else it returns 0.
So these are comparison operators.
We also have what we call binary operators.
These operators will process the variable's binary data directly.
We'll go into more details later on,
because it's not very useful for now.
But it allows to process each of the bits contained in variables.
Then we have shortcuts,
which allow to facilitate the reading.
For instance we can write "a += 10", that's just like
writing "a = a + 10".
We could write "a++", which is the same as
writing "a = a + 1".
We can write "/=", that's the same
as doing a division.
Those are just means to simplify writing.
There are some special expression elements.
For example 'A' returns the ASCII code
for the character between apostrophes.
Actually, the ASCII code for "A" is 65.
ASCII codes are extremely important, as they allow us to
display characters.
There's an ASCII table, but we'll get back to this later on.
We have the operator SIZEOF.
We write "sizeof",
the type of variable, of directly a variable,
and this will return the size this variable take up in the memory.
A last one: if we add an "&" before a variable,
it'll return the address of this variable, in the memory.
There's what we call a ternary operator,
even if we rarely use it.
The syntax is as follows : and expression, "?",
a 2nd expression, ":", a 3rd expression,
and it'll evaluate the fist expression.
If the expression isn't NULL, it'll evaluate the second, and
return it as a value.
Or else, it'll evaluate the third expression, and return it as a value.
So, it's a conditional expression.
The last point, is what we call character strings.
A string is a series of characters
between inverted commas.
This will allocate memory for the
characters between inverted commas.
It'll add a "\0" in the end, and it'll return the address
of the first character.
We've seen, when we listed types, that there's a particular type...
Pointers.
A pointer is a variable like the others,
except that instead of storing data,
it'll store the address of another variable,
well at least the data's address.
It's a pointer to something,
so, as it name suggests,
it contains the address of something.
How to declare a pointer ?
First we have to declare the type of what we point to,
meaning the variable's type
whose address we want to store.
So we write the type, "*", the name.
An example : If I write "int *p",
"p" stores the address of a variable of type int.
How do we use them?
Quite simply.
Once we've declared a pointer
of type int,
as I did just there.
We write "p = &a".
We'll set the address of "a" in "p".
Then we'll use "*p".
We do "p = 1;"
it'll set "1" inside the address pointed by "p",
It's the same as writing "a = 1",
as "p" contains the address of "a",
So if "p" contains the address of "a",
"*p" is the same thing as "a",
It's the same memory area, the same address
and the same type.
Basically,
we can say that "*name"
so "*" the name of a variable, of type pointer,
is the object of type "type"
whose addresses is stored in "name".
That's very important.
You must systematically refer to this definition.
When I have a pointer called "name",
of type "type",
*name is the object of type "type", stored in "name.
So we have an arithmetics system.
Let's take an array "tab[42]",
So "p", an object of type pointer, which stores
the address of tab's first element.
If we write "*(p + x)", we access the value located at the position "x"
of our array,
same as if we wrote "tab[x]".
So. Up till now,
we've seen variable declarations,
instructions,
and now we're left with control structures.
In C, there are several control structures.
We'll see 3.
Actually, we'll see 4.
Because 2 of them are very much alike.
The first is...
the control structure IF.
It's quite simple :
we write "if (expression)"
and then, an instruction.
This instruction can be a block,
which means it can contain several instructions,
and declarations.
How does it work? It's simple :
it evaluates the expression.
So we're going to calculate the result of the expression.
If the expression returns 0, it doesn't do anything.
if it returns something else than 0, it'll execute the instruction.
It's a simple test, and quite practical to use.
There's a more elaborated version
which is "if (expression)
else "
As you can imagine, it evaluates the expression.
If the expression is worth 0, it executes the 2nd expression.
If the expression is worth 1, it executes the 1st expression.
It's a rather simple thing.
Second control structure, the structure WHILE.
The structure WHILE is quite simple : "while (expression),
and an instruction.
The process is a little different.
The WHILE evaluates the expression.
If the expression us worth 0, it stops.
If it's worth something other than 0,
we'll execute the instruction.
So far, it's just like with an IF,
except that instead of stopping here, we loop.
Which means we re-evaluate the expression.
If the expression is worth 0, we stop, else, we execute the instruction again,
and we go back to the start.
As it names suggests, we'll execute the instruction while
the expression isn't worth 0.
That's how all loops work.
That's how you'll use them during this piscine.
There are other control structures, but you'll just use these ones
for now.
The last control structure :
The structure RETURN, which allows to
return a value at the exit of a function.
As we've seen, the function takes parameters as entries,
and returns a value upon exit.
RETURN allows us to return this value.
return(_) calculates the expression, and stops the function.
This means that if there are other instructions after this "return",
they won't be executed.
The function's return value will be the result of the expression.
There's another type of RETURN without a return value,
meant for a particular type of function
we haven't seen yet,
but you'll see that later.
Those are functions that can't return values,
and which have a different syntax.
That's it for this lesson about C,
or at least for what you need for this Piscine.